<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc emoticonic="yes"?>
<?rfc private=" "?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>

<rfc>

<front> 
<title abbrev="Profile Tutorial">
How to Write Profiles for the BEEPCORE-C Library
</title>

<author initials="D." surname="New" fullname="Darren New">
<organization/>

<address>
<postal>
<street>5390 Caminito Exquisito</street>
<city>San Diego</city>
<region>CA</region>
<code>92130</code>
<country>US</country>
</postal>

<phone>+1 858 350 9733</phone>
<email>dnew@san.rr.com</email>
</address>
</author>

<date month="November" year="2001"/>
</front>

<middle>



<section title="Introduction">

<t> This document gives a brief tutorial on implementing profiles
appropriately. It assumes the reader has a fair familiarity with BEEP as
defined in RFC3080. </t>

<t> The CBEEP library and its supporting code is simple to use for simple
applications, yet it is capable of surprisingly complex applications. The
system consists of four levels of code: </t>

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="Core:">The "core" library is embodied in CBEEP.c and its
supporting files. The "core" refers to the part of the code directly
responsible for implementing RFC3080 and RFC3081 syntax and semantics. It is
portable. It includes no I/O or memory management, which allows it to be used
in a wide variety of applications and environments. However, it lacks a number
of features one might expect to find in every BEEP application, such as a
mapping of URIs onto different profile implementations. </t>

<t hangText="Wrapper:">The "wrapper" library wraps around the core library
and provides services such as I/O, synchronization, thread creation and
termination, and dispatch of messages to separate independent implementations,
based on the profile's URI. </t>

<t hangText="Profile Implementation:">Each "profile implementation"
implements one or more profiles as defined by their URIs and the RFCs
describing their operation. Each profile implementation is responsible for
reacting to events sent to it in the form of messages, replies, initialization
and finalization from the wrapper, and so on. </t>

<t hangText="Application:">Each "application" invokes at least one wrapper.
The application is responsible for finding all the profile implementations of
interest, opening the underlying TCP socket, creating a wrapper, and otherwise
dealing with inter-profile communication, inter-wrapper communication, and
configuration. </t>

</list>

<t> The library comes with an application that reads a simple configuration
file and starts either a listening server or an initiating client. This
application can be replaced for more sophisticated applications that may have
connections to multiple peers at the same time, for example. </t>

<t> This tutorial describes how to create profile implementations and
applications that take advantage of the wrapper that comes with the library.
</t>

</section>

<?rfc include='IncludeConcepts' ?>

<section title="Creating a Simple Profile">

<t> Creating a "simple" profile is straightforward. A simple profile is one
that runs over a single channel, independent of other channels or sessions, and
which is not a tuning profile. For example, a profile that echoes back any
messages received would be a simple profile. A profile that performs a database
search and returns the results would be a simple profile. A simple profile
might both initiate requests and respond to requests. </t>

<t> In contrast, TLS is a more complex profile, since it manages tuning resets.
A profile that shares information
amongst several sessions (such as a multi-user game server profile) would be
complex. A profile that starts other profiles or establishes other BEEP
connections would be considered complex. However, all these cases are possible
to handle easily once the basics of simple profiles are understood. </t>

<t> Each simple profile implementation has a listening portion and an
initiating portion. The lines may be a bit blurry. For example, a database
server may spontaneously inform a client that an earlier search result has been
invalidated by the arrival of new data at the server. Generally, however, there
will be a part of the profile designed to accept requests, and another part
designed to generate requests. But first we need to discuss registration. </t>

<section title="Registering Profiles">

<t> Registering a profile consists primarily of creating a profile registration
structure and making it available to the application in the way the application
expects. For example, in dynamically loaded profile instances, the wrapper will
define a function call it will invoke after loading a library. This function
will be expected to return a linked list of all the profile registration
structures for all profiles implemented in that library.</t>

<t> Each registration structure has the following elements: </t>

<list style="hanging">

<t hangText="uri:">The URI of the profile being implemented. This can be
registered with IANA for standardized profiles. Note that each wrapper allows
only one registration for each URI; that is, one cannot register multiple
registrations with the same value for the URI. </t>

<t hangText="next:">The next registration in the list of registrations. Used
for when a single implementation implements multiple profiles. </t>

<t hangText="initiator_modes:">A string (char *) of comma-separated values. Each
value names one "mode" in which this profile will be initialized, but in which
this profile's URI will not be advertised in the greeting. </t>

<t hangText="listener_modes:">A string (char *) of comma-separated values. Each
value names one "mode" in which this profile will be initialized and in which
this profile's URI will be advertised in the greeting. </t>

<t hangText="full_messages:">An integer that serves as a boolean value. If
true, the profile is only informed of frame arrival when a complete message has
arrived. That is, the profile will not be informed of frames with the more flag
in the header having "*" as a value. </t>

<t hangText="thread_per_channel:">An integer that serves as a boolean value. If true, the profile has a thread dedicated to it for as long as the channel is open. If false, the profile gets a thread from the threadpool for the duration of the execution of one |"pro_| function. </t>

<t hangText="user_ptr:">A void_t that you can use for whatever you want.</t>

<t hangText="Function pointers:">A table of pointers to functions.
There is one pointer for each function whose name starts with |"pro_|. These are
the functions invoked by the wrapper. </t>

</list>

<t> When the wrapper wishes to invoke one of the functions, it always passes in
either a pointer to the profile registration structure or a pointer to the
profile instance, depending on the function. Functions called when no profile
instances exist get only a pointer to the registration structure. The others
get a pointer to the instance structure, which in turn contains a pointer to
the registration structure. </t>

</section> <!-- Registering Profiles -->

<section title="Accepting Requests">

<t> Once a profile implementation is registered with a wrapper, the
implementation is ready to be invoked. The wrapper invokes |"pro_connection_init|
(indirectly via the profile registration structure) as soon as the wrapper is
started. Since no channels are open yet, a simple profile needn't do anything.
However, if there is configuration to be loaded or database access to be
obtained or something like this, |"pro_connection_init| is where an implementation
would deal with that.</t>

<t>Since in this part of the tutorial we are dealing with the listening side,
our profile registration includes the application's default mode in its
"listener_modes" pointer.
In most cases,
your profile doesn't care whether it's running over an encrypted
session or not,
so your profile usually consults a configuration file,
using the value "plaintext,encrypted" as a default.
Of course,
if your profile requires privacy,
e.g., the SASL PLAIN profile,
then you should hard-wire this accordingly.</t>

<t> When the wrapper's mode is such that the profile is available,
|"pro_session_init| will be called as well. Again, for this simplest of profiles,
nothing needs to be done.</t>

<t> Eventually, when the remote peer delivers its greeting, the wrapper will
invoke |"pro_greeting_confirmation|. This is primarily useful for an initiating
profile, so we'll defer the discussion of that function until later. </t>

<t> The first time at which a trivial listener profile actually needs to do
something significant is when the remote peer opens a channel on that profile.
When this happens, the wrapper will call |"pro_start_indication| with two
arguments. The first will be the address of a newly allocated profile instance
structure. The wrapper fills in all fields of interest in the structure.
The second argument is a pointer to a profile structure which
represents one &lt;profile&gt; element
within the &lt;start&gt; element.</t>

<t> When the |"pro_start_indication| entry is called, the profile implementation
is expected to process the profile piggyback data and decide whether to open
the channel. The very first call the profile instance makes to the wrapper must
be a call to |"bpc_start_response|. That function takes three parameters:
a channel pointer (taken from the profile instance),
a single profile structure (possibly with the piggyback data),
and a diagnostic structure indicating the reason the channel could not
be opened.
If the channel opens successfully but the profile wishes to return an error as
piggyback data, then the diagnostic pointer must be NULL,
the error must be encoded as piggyback data. If the diagnostic pointer
is non-NULL, the
profile instance will be immediately reaped.</t>

<t> It should be noted that the wrapper itself might refuse to open a channel
before the profile implementation sees any indication that the remote peer
tried to start a channel. This would be the case if the wrapper itself is low
on resources, for example. </t>

<t> Assuming the profile instance has allowed the channel to start, it should expect to start receiving messages. The
three functions that might be called during normal processing are
|"pro_frame_available|, |"pro_message_available|, and |"pro_window_full|.
The first two
are straightforward. They inform the instance that either a frame has been
received, or a frame with the "more" header flag set to "." has arrived. Only
one of these will be called, depending on whether the "full_messages" flag is
set in the registration. Assuming that we are interested in full messages only,
when the last frame of a message arrives for our channel, the
|"pro_message_available| function will be invoked. </t>

<t> It is important to note that when |"pro_message_available| (or
|"pro_frame_available|) is invoked, the wrapper has not done anything with the
message (or frame).
The profile implementation is expected to call |"bpc_query_message| (or
|"bpc_query_frame|) in order to obtain the frames. The implementation
must also call 
|"bpc_frame_destroy| when it is finished with the frames so fetched; this opens up
the receiving window on the channel again. |"bpc_frame_aggregate| is useful for
profiles that deal with messages rather than frames, as it can take the result
from |"bpc_query_message| and turn it into a single contiguous frame as
if it had been received that way.</t>

<t> For convenience, the last character after the payload on an incoming frame
is set to '\0' as well, allowing simple string handling for text-oriented
protocols. However, no other processing is done on the body of the message. In
particular, the profile implementation is expected to process the MIME headers
and deal with any content-transfer-encoding introduced by the remote peer, to
parse any XML, to deal with end-of-line translations, and so on. </t>

<t> Once the profile implementation has decided how to answer a message, it
allocates a frame using |"bpc_buffer_allocate| and then calls |"bpc_send|.
The implementation must provide all values of interest,
such as the message type, channel number,
message number, answer number, and the "more" flag. The size field is already
set to the original requested size; this value can be decreased but not
increased. The payload pointer should not be modified; instead, you should copy
your payload to where the payload pointer points. For convenience, there is at
least one extra character of space after the requested payload size, so it's
legal to use strcpy (which copies the extra '\0') without running off the end
of the allocated space. The wrapper will take care of deallocating the
frame once it has been sent.  </t>

<t> Eventually, the remote peer will tire of invoking the services of this
profile and will close the channel. When this happens, the wrapper will call
|"pro_close_indication|. This function is told whether it is the local or remote
peer trying to close the channel and whether it is the session or just the
channel being closed. |"pro_close_indication| decides whether it is allowable to
close and calls |"bpc_close_response| with a 
a channel pointer (taken from the profile instance),
and a diagnostic.
If the dignostic is non-NULL,
That diagnostic will be returned as an &lt;error&gt; element in response to the
close, and the close will not occur. </t>

<t> The profile instance, upon agreeing to close, should stop sending MSG
messages. However, it should continue to process any MSG messages it receives,
answering them. It should also process any reply frames it receives, discarding
them. </t>

<t> Eventually, when both sides settle down, |"pro_close_confirmation| will be
called.
This tells the profile instance whether the close has actually happened.
If so,
the profile module should deallocate any additional
resources that particular instance was using.</t>

<t> The only difficult parts of this process are handing of start indications
and message arrivals. For the simplest of profiles, the other functionality is
trivial. </t>


</section> <!-- Accepting Requests -->

<section title="Generating Requests">

<t> On the other side of the connection is the initiating profile. It too supplies a profile registration structure. It too is initialized for the process and for the session.  </t>

<t> The first significant difference is that the "client" side must initiate
the connection, rather than listening for an incoming connection. This is part
of the application, rather than part of the profile implementation, but it
could have interactions with the profile implementation. We'll get into that
more below. </t>

<t>The second significant difference is that the "client" side must
also start one or more channels.
There are two ways of doing this.
First,
the profile module can provide additional entry points;
Alternatively,
when the wrapper makes the |"pro_greeting_confirmation| call,
the profile module may decide to start one or more channels.
(We'll look at these choices in more detail later on.)
Regardless,
|"bp_start_request| is used to start a channel.</t>

<t>|"bp_start_request| takes many arguments:
a pointer to a wrapper,
the channel/message number to use for the request,
a pointer to a profile structure,
the serverName to request,
a callback function,
and a client-data pointer.
Calling
|"bp_start_request| generates the &lt;start&gt; message. The callback function is
called when the remote peer answers the &lt;start&gt; message with either a
&lt;profile&gt; or an &lt;error&gt; element. When this happens, the callback is
called with a channel pointer, a diagnostic pointer, and the client-data.
If the channel is going to be opened,
the diagnostic pointer is NULL;
otherwise,
the channel pointer should be ignored.
If the channel is being started,
a new profile instance structure has been
initialized at this time, but no call has been made to any of the |"pro_|
functions it has registered. The callback function should take care not to
block. One common use of the callback is to copy information from the passed
client-data pointer into the user fields of the profile instance.</t>

<t>If the channel is started,
then after the callback returns,
then |"pro_start_confirmation| is called on the new profile instance.</t> 

<t> Once the profile instance receives this call, it can start generating
messages. It simply allocates a frame with |"bpc_buffer_allocate|, fills in the
payload, and calls |"bpc_send| to dispatch it. Calls to
|"pro_message_available| (or |"pro_frame_available|)
result in calls to |"bpc_query_message| (or |"bpc_query_frame|) and the subsequent
handling of the received replies. </t>

<t> After a while, the profile instance tires of sending echoes and decides to
close the channel. It simply stops sending MSG frames and calls
bpc_close_request, passing the channel pointer.
in the wrapper and the channel number of interest,
a callback function,
and a client-data pointer.
While waiting for the answer, the profile must continue to deal with any
incoming MSG frames, generating replies as appropriate. It should also deal
with any replies to outstanding messages it has sent. However, it should avoid
initiating new MSG frames until the close request has been confirmed. </t>

<t>The callback function is
called when the remote peer answers the &lt;close&gt; message with either a
&lt;ok&gt; or an &lt;error&gt; element. When this happens, the callback is
called with a channel pointer, a diagnostic pointer, and the client-data.
If the channel is going to be closed,
the diagnostic pointer is NULL.
Regardless,
the wrapper will call |"pro_close_confirmation| to indicate what happened.
If the channel was closed,
the profile module should deallocate any additional
resources that particular instance was using.</t>

<t> At any point, |"bp_shutdown| may be invoked. This immediately aborts
all profiles and cleans up, then signals that it has finished. </t>

</section> <!-- Generating Requests -->

<section title="Who Gets to Start a Channel?">

<t> The first question that might come to mind is "how do I actually arrange to
get the initiating profile started?" In other words, who calls
|"bp_start_request|? There are two places from which this function can be
invoked. First, a profile can be completely "stand-alone," invoking the
|"bp_start_request| from the |"pro_greeting_confirmation| call, as described.
Alternately, the application itself could watch for the greeting to be received
and invoke |"bp_start_request|. Let's take a look at these two possibilities.
</t>

<t> For the first possibility, one might imagine a chat client that reads from
the command line the chat server to which the user wishes to connect. In this
case, the application would connect to the indicated server and start the
wrapper. The reception of the greeting would trigger the profile implementation
to open a window into which the user can type messages and into which the
profile implementation posts messages received. </t>

<t> For the second possibility, imagine a chat client that opens a window into
which a user can type requests to connect. In this case, the application must
open the window and handle the I/O with the window. When the user enters the
name of the server to which he wishes to be connected, the application reads
and interprets this command. It opens the socket and starts the wrapper on the
socket, then waits for a greeting. When the greeting is received, the
application issues the |"bp_start_request|, passing the address of the window as
the client data, which is in turn passed on to the profile instance. When
messages are received, the profile instance uses the saved window pointer to
post the messages to the window. </t>

</section> <!-- Passing Information to the Profile Instance -->

</section> <!-- Creating a Simple Profile -->

<section title="Advanced Topics">

<t> There are a number of topics that do not arise when dealing with simple
profiles. However, these topics do arise when dealing with very complicated
profiles. These complications are discussed here. </t>

<section title="Starting Other Profiles">

<t> Probably the most common need will be starting a TLS or SASL profile.
Generally, tuning profiles (in the RFC3080 meaning of the word) will
provide an API to start them. This API will allow the application to provide
information that is not included in the &lt;start&gt; request, such as the
certificate files the TLS implementation is to use, or the user name and
password that the SASL implementation is to use. It is expected that tuning
profiles will also accept a callback to be called when tuning completes, but
this will vary between implementations. </t>

<t> Alternately, some profiles may start themselves when so configured and they
receive an appropriate |"pro_greeting_confirmation|. Inspect the documentation for
individual profile implementations to determine this. </t>

</section> <!-- Starting Other Profiles -->

<section title="Window Overruns">

<t> A window overrun occurs when the profile implementation wishes to handle
only complete messages, but a complete message does not fit into the available
channel window size. In this case, additional frames cannot be received without
action on the profile's part, but the profile will not take action until
additional frames are received. </t>

<t> If a profile expects messages of an arbitrarily large size, it should
handle the messages a frame at a time. There is no other reasonable way to
behave if the size of messages is truly unbounded. For example, if a request
provides a file name and the response provides the file's contents as one giant
RPY, the file contents must be written to disk (or a different socket) as it
arrives, since it might be larger than memory. </t>

<t> If a profile expects messages whose size is limited, it should set the
channel receive window size to be somewhat larger than the maximum expected
message size. In this case, it is a protocol error if the window fills without
a complete message being present. For example, if the profile fetches the
current time from the peer in ISO format, it is safe to expect a conforming
peer will not send more than 4K in response to the request. If the default
window fills up without a complete message for this profile, it is safe to
assume the remote peer is in error. </t>

<t> Thus, there are several cures for the situation in which the receive window
fills without a complete message being present. The profile instance can handle
incoming messages one frame at a time. The profile instance can send a
preemptive &lt;error&gt; and ignore the message, discarding all present and
future frames until it gets to the final frame. The profile instance can
increase the size of the receive window, allowing more frames to be sent. </t>

</section> <!-- Window Overruns -->

<section title="Tuning Resets">

<t> A tuning reset occurs when a tuning profile has changed the underlying
protocol used on the socket and wishes to start a new session with a new
greeting. [!@!@ OTHER THAN THAT, WE'LL DOCUMENT IT MORE LATER.] </t>

</section> <!-- Tuning Resets -->

<section title="Multiple Sessions">

<t> There are also several situations in which a profile might wish to deal
with multiple interacting sessions at once. In the simplest case, the number of
sessions being managed is strictly limited. For example, imagine a profile
designed to run on a firewall, granting access to machines inside the firewall
based on SASL logins to the firewall machine. In this case, there would be the
listening profile that accepts the connection. After the remote peer has logged
in properly, it can request a connection to a machine inside the firewall by
starting this profile. The profile instance would receive the start indication
and attempt to open a socket to the machine indicated in the piggyback data.
When that socket connected, the profile instance would start a new wrapper, a
second wrapper to handle the interactions on the new socket. Then a channel
would be started on the second wrapper, and interactions between the two active
profile implementations would need to be coordinated by those profiles. 
(Incidentally, this is known as the TUNNEL profile.) </t>

<t> As another example, imagine a multi-user game server. This server would
maintain a number of listening wrappers within the same UNIX process. Messages
coming in from one wrapper would need to be coordinated with messages coming in
from other wrappers, and perhaps copied and sent out to other wrappers.
Different channels on the same session might be carrying inter-player
conversation, images of the surroundings, viewpoint information, and so on.
Such inter-session communication is left up to the application to coordinate.
</t>

</section> <!-- Multiple Sessions -->
</section> <!-- Advanced Topics -->

<!--

<section title="Threading Models">

<t> A single wrapper instance can support multiple threading models if multiple
channels are open to different profiles. The wrapper invokes the profile
implementation via the functions whose name starts with |"pro_|, all of which are
listed in a profile registration structure. The main thread for the wrapper
invokes these functions directly, rather than providing any built-in threading
or other concurrency management. Other than the |"pro_| functions which take a
profile registration structure pointer rather than a profile instance pointer,
the |"pro_| functions should never block. That is, it is acceptable to block
during registration of a profile, but once a channel is open, profile instances
should avoid blocking in these calls. This is why none of the |"pro_| instance
functions returns a value. Note that the |"bp_| functions never block either.
Therefore, all blocking must be managed by a third party.  </t>

<t> This third party takes the form of a "library registration." [WE NEED A
BETTER NAME FOR THIS.] Essentially, each |"pro_| function call may be intercepted
by a different function that provides for the management of one or more threads
for that profile instance. These library registrations are not actual profile
registrations, but they require the full list of all the |"pro_| functions, so
using a profile registration structure to describe them is reasonable in a
language like C, which has no inheritance.  </t>

<t> If a particular profile implementation does not wish to use threads at all
because it never blocks, it simply leaves the "layer" pointer in its
registration structure set to NULL. Examples of these might be an "echo"
profile, a "what time is it" profile, or other such simple query profiles. When
a frame arrives for an echo profile, it can simply call |"bpc_query_frame|,
copy the read frame into the created frame with appropriate
header modifications, call |"bpc_send| with the created frame, and
|"bpc_frame_destroy| with the read frame. None of these functions block, so
starting them in a different thread would be pointless. </t>

<t> If a very complex profile implementation wishes to use one or more threads
in its implementation, it can of course have knowledge of the underlying
threading model and use that, "hand crafting" a specific threading and event
management model. A complex real-time game server or something like an APEX
message routing relay might want to use such a complicated mechanism, wherein
different profile instances are communicating between wrappers to facilitate
inter-session conversations. Again, in this case, the "layer" pointer would be
NULL, and the profile implementation would have to implement all the logic
necessary to avoid blocking.  </t>

<t> The intermediate level of complexity is provided in libraries supplied
along with the wrapper library. There are three [EVENTUALLY] choices provided.
</t>

<list style="symbols">

<t> The first allocates and commits a single thread to each profile, and
processes |"pro_| calls sequentially as they arrive, blocking on a semaphore when
all events from the wrapper have been processed for now. This is a good choice
for a simple application with few concurrent wrappers and few concurrent
channels open. </t>

<t>The second maintains a pool of threads, allocating one to a profile instance
whenever an event arrives (in the form of a call to a |"pro_| function), letting
it process all outstanding events, and then perhaps reassigning that thread to
a different profile instance in this or another. This is a good choice in an
application with many concurrent wrappers with many channels being opened and
closed. </t>

<t> The third maintains a pool of threads, and allocates one thread to each
event. The profile instance must take care if using this model, as the
intention is that multiple events may be handled concurrently in the profile
implementation. In other words, if three messages arrive at once, it is
possible there will be three threads running at the same time to handle the
channel. Of course, this somewhat changes the semantics of the profile
functions. It might be useful in a database query system that handles
transactional locking and such automatically. However, using this library
requires the profile implementation author to be aware of the reentrancy
problems. </t>

</list>

<t> Simply put, the library registration is responsible for disassociating the
wrapper from the profile instance using threads. The semantics of the calls are
maintained by the library, so simply chose one that provides the appropriate
level of performance. </t>

<section title="How It Works">

<t> The mechanism of library registrations might be simpler to understand with
a brief look at the working of a simple one. </t>

<t> First, the interface with the wrapper: When a wrapper instance is about to
invoke a |"pro_| function on a profile instance, it follows the pointer from the
profile instance to its registration structure. However, before calling the
|"pro_| function registered there, it checks the "layer" pointer. If that's set,
the wrapper follows the pointer and uses that registration structure to find
the proper |"pro_| function pointer. It then calls this function directly,
expecting it to return immediately, passing it the documented arguments. </t>

<t> The function pointer actually points into a library rather than the profile
instance, in this case. The library uses the profile instance pointer, which is
always supplied during such a call, to find the profile instance. The library
is then responsible for eventually invoking the original function to which the
profile instance directly points. </t>

<t> For example, in the library providing a dedicated thread per profile
instance, the |"pro_start_confirmation| call is intercepted by the library. At
this point, the library would create a semaphore, an event queue, and a thread.
It would start the thread and have it block on the semaphore. </t>

<t> For the start confirmation and subsequent messages, the library marshals
the arguments to the function into a newly allocated structure, links the
structure to the queue in the profile instance, and signals the semaphore to
wake the thread. The thread wakes, pulls the event from the queue, and invokes
the function in the profile registration structure to which the profile
instance directly points.  </t>

<t> If more |"pro_| functions are called before the thread is finished, they will
be queued on the event queue by the library, handled in turn by the dedicated
thread. </t>

</section How It Works 

</section Threading Models

-->

<section title="Sample Code and Execution">

<t>The best way to understand what's going on is to look at the file
|"profiles/null-profiles.c| &#151; it shows everything you need to
know when writing a simple profile.</t>

<section title="For Those Reading Source Code">

<t> This section takes a quick look at starting a channel on an
already-established session, tracking the creation of various private data
structures. The information presented here is not necessary for the use of the
libraries, but it may help to explain some concepts to those looking at the
source code. </t>

<t> The first example shows a machine named ALPHA opening a channel to its peer named BETA, and the channel open succeeding. </t>

<list type="numbers">

<t> ALPHA's application layer calls |"bp_start_request|. </t>

<t> ALPHA's wrapper remembers the callback and user data, then calls blu_start_request. </t>

<t> ALPHA's core library creates a "struct channel", marks it as half open, formats the XML &lt;start&gt; message, and queues it on channel zero. </t>

<t> ALPHA's wrapper is notified (via notify_lower) that octets are ready, and those octets are copied to the socket. </t>

<t> BETA receives the header, allocates a frame, and receives the body into the frame. </t>

<t> BETA queues the completely-received frame onto its own channel zero structure, and calls notify_upper. </t>

<t> BETA's wrapper calls blu_chan0_parse to receive the message. blu_chan0_parse interprets the XML, creates a channel structure, and marks it as half-started. It then returns the chan0_msg. </t> 

<t> BETA's wrapper examines the chan0_msg, decides which profile to instantiate, creates a profile instance, and calls |"pro_start_indication|. </t>

<t> BETA's profile handles the piggyback data (if any) and returns a successful result via |"bpc_start_response|. </t>

<t> BETA's wrapper passes the response to blu_chan0_reply. blu_chan0_reply matches the response against the request, sees that it is a &lt;profile&gt; and not an &lt;error&gt;, and marks the channel as fully open. It then creates the XML and queues it on channel zero. </t>

<t> BETA's wrapper is notified via notify_lower that octets are waiting, and the wrapper copies them to the socket. </t>

<t> ALPHA's wrapper pulls the octets off the socket, and stores them into the library. </t>

<t> When the complete frame has arrived, ALPHA's core library calls notify_upper to inform ALPHA's wrapper that a channel zero message is ready. </t>

<t> ALPHA's wrapper calls blu_chan0_parse. blu_chan0_parse parses the XML and constructs a chan0_msg. blu_chan0_parse sees that the chan0_msg is a positive response to the chan0_msg sent as a request earlier and marks the associated channel as fully open, then returns the chan0_msg to the wrapper. </t>

<t> ALPHA's wrapper sees the positive confirmation, creates a profile instance for the profile selected by BETA. It then invokes the remembered callback, and then invokes the |"pro_start_confirmation|. </t>

</list>

</section> <!-- For Those Reading Source Code -->

</section> <!-- Sample Code and Execution -->

</middle>

<back>

<section title="Copyright and License">

<t>Blocks Public License
<vspace blankLines='0' />
Copyright (c) 2000, Invisible Worlds, Inc. 
<vspace blankLines='0' />
All rights reserved.</t>

<t>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without 
modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met: 
<list style='symbols'>
<t>Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, 
  this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</t>

<t>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice, 
  this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation 
  and/or other materials provided with the distribution.</t>

<t>Neither the name, trademarks, or tradenames of Invisible Worlds, Inc., nor 
  the names, trademarks, or tradenames of its contributors may be used to 
  endorse or promote products derived from this software without specific 
  prior written permission.</t>
</list>
THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS ``AS IS'' 
AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE 
IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE 
DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL INVISIBLE WORLDS OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR 
ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES 
(INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; 
LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND 
ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT 
(INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS 
SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</t>
</section>
</back>
</rfc>

